我开始了，大家能看到我分享的屏幕吗？
I started and everybody could see my screen that I shared?
我希望每个人都能听到我说话。
And I hope everybody can hear me.
让我。
Let me.
我想是好的。
I think we're good.
好的，今天我要讨论一下文件系统，
Okay, so I'm going to talk about file system today
我们会用三节课来讲解文件系统，
and going to be actually going to spend three lectures on file systems,
两节在 xv6 环境中，一节在 Linux 环境中。
two in the context of xv6 and one in the context of Linux.
实际上，这是关于 xv6 的最后一个话题，
In fact, this is the last topic, that we're covering of xv6,
这周过后，我们基本上完成了 xv6 。
after this week, we're basically done with xv6.
所以，文件系统，你们都知道，并使用它，
So, you know file systems, you all know them, you use them,
它是操作系统中最面向用户的方面之一，
they're one of the most sort of user facing aspects of an operating system,
除了 shell 。
in addition to the shell.
所以，我们现在想知道，
And so, we want to understand now
而这几节课讲的就是，
and the set of lectures actually
文件系统底层到底发生了什么，
what it really happens under the hoods
以及它是如何实现的。
and how is the file system is implemented.
这让人兴奋，因为你一直在使用它。
And that's sort of exciting, because you know you use them all the time.
也许在深入任何细节之前，我们先来问个问题，
And maybe here to start off with a question before diving in any of the details,
在某种程度上，因为你几乎每天都在使用文件系统，
I, in one way you know, since you use file systems are almost daily,
在某种程度上， xv6 文件系统不同于
in one way is the xv6 file system different than
你日常使用的文件系统。
the file system that you're using in the day-to-day work.
我会把它们提供给大家，
Maybe I'll collect them to people
看看他们是怎么想的。
and see what they think.
比如 Kendall ， Kendall Garner 。
For example Kendall, Kendall Garner, what.
你有没有注意到 xv6 有什么不同或相似之处？
Did you notice anything particular about xv6 that is different or similar.
我不确定我们能不能听到你， Kendall 。
I'm not sure we can hear your, Kendall.
我在这里。
Here I am.
好的。
Yeah.
Yeah okay.
好的。
Yeah.
所以其中一个问题就是大小，
So one of the problems is size
或者至少 xv6 支持的文件的大小
or at least the size of the files that xv6 support
比许多其他文件系统小得多，
are much less than a lot of other file systems,
另外，有些文件的名称相对较短。
also the names for some files are relatively short.
还有一个功能，更多的是使用[][]，
And another feature, it's more just to use [] [],
它没有，
it doesn't,
我认为它没有文件系统的写入时复制。
I don't think it has a copy-on-write for a file system.
很好，有什么相似之处。
Good, in what way is similar.
它在总体结构上是相似的，
It's similar in the general structure,
所以有文件名，
so the idea of you have file names,
有 inode ，目录等等。
you have the inodes, directories, and all that.
是的，不错。
Yeah, seems good.
那 Adella Yang 呢。
And how about Adella Yang.
你如何比较 xv6 文件系统与你使用的文件系统。
How do you compare xv6 file system to the file system you use.
抱歉，是什么。
Sorry, what is that.
问题是，你会如何，
The question is like how would you,
你如何比较 xv6 文件系统
how would you compare the xv6 file system
与你在日常生活中使用的文件系统，
to the file system you might be using in daily life
或者在你的笔记本电脑上，
or on your laptop
不管你用的是什么电脑。
whatever computer you're using.
有没有相似之处。
Any similarities.
是的，比如文件系统的路径系统，
Yeah, like the the file system paths system,
比如路径和文件系统是分层的。
like paths and file system are [] hierarchical.
是的，这是一个很好的观点。
Yep, that's a good point.
好的，所以，
Okay, so you know,
所以让我，稍微深入一点，
so let me, so dive in a little bit
稍微谈一下文件系统的属性，
and sort of talk a little bit about properties of file systems,
有点[突出]，
you know sort of stand out,
有一个我想你刚才在这里提到的，
and one I think you know you just mentioned here,
是用户友好的命名，
[] is user-friendly, user-friendly names,
特别是路径名，它的层次结构，
in particular path names, you know hierarchy to, hierarchy to them,
帮助人们组织他们的文件和目录，
to help people to organize their files and directories or folders
无论你想使用什么术语，
whatever term you want to use
它使人们共享文件更方便，
and it makes it easy for you know people to share files
在用户和进程之间。
you know between users and processes.
你可以方便地给它们命名。
You can name them with conveniently to remember names.
然后可能最重要的是，
And then probably most importantly,
至少为目前我们在 xv6 中看到的所有子系统做好了准备，
prepared at least for all the subsystems, that we've looked so far in xv6
它们提供了持久化存储，
and they provide persistence,
或者有时候被称为耐久性。
or sometimes that's called durability.
我的意思是，如果你关掉电脑，
With that, I mean like if you turn off your computer,
你做了一些工作，
you did some work,
关掉了电脑或者笔记本电脑，
you turn off your computer or turn off your laptop,
几天后你回来，
and then a couple days later you come back,
重新打开电脑，
you turn your computer on,
文件还在那里，
the files are still there,
你可以继续使用它们工作。
and you continue working with them.
这不同于进程，
Which is different from like processes
或者目前为止我们看到的资源，
or the thing of the resources that we've seen so far,
如果计算机重新启动，它们消失了，
which basically you know the computer reboots, you know they're gone
你必须重新开始，
and you have to start up again,
但是文件系统可以提供这种持久性。
but file systems can provide this persistence.
所以它们是，你们所有人都在使用它们，
And so they're you know all of you using them,
接下来几节课我们要做的是，
and what we're gonna be doing in the next couple lectures is
了解它在内部是如何工作的。
actually understanding how to actually work internally.
这很有趣，有很多原因。
And this is interesting for a number of reasons.
一个是抽象本身，它是有用的。
One you know the abstraction itself, it's just useful.
所以理解幕后很有趣，
And so it's interesting to understand under the hood,
实际上，它的抽象是如何实现的。
it's actually how do abstraction is actually implemented.
这里面有几个关键的有趣的方面。
It turns out there's a couple key interesting aspects.
一个是崩溃安全，
One is crash safety,
它是这种情况，
you'd like it to be the case
比如在文件系统操作期间，
that you know if for example during the file system operation,
计算机崩溃了，
the computer crashes,
在重启后，文件系统仍然保持完好，
that after reboot basically file system still intact,
文件系统的所有变量仍然存在，
you know all the variants of the file systems still hold
而且你可以访问你的大部分文件，
and that you can actually get access to most of your files,
这会是一场灾难，
it would be a disaster
如果计算机在文件系统操作过程中崩溃，
if the computer crashed in the middle of file system operation,
你重新启动，但是没有了文件系统，
you reboot and there's no file system anymore,
或者磁盘上的数据结构已损坏，
or you know the data structure on disk have been garbled
你丢失了它们。
and you lost them.
所以这是一个非常重要的话题，[]
And so this actually turns out to be a really important topic and involved
所以我们将在周三讨论这个，
and so we're going to talk about that on Wednesday,
这是周三课程的主要话题。
this is basically the main topic for Wednesday's lecture.
然后有一个一般性问题，
Then there's sort of a general question
关于文件系统在磁盘上如何安排。
about how to layout the file system on disk.
你知道，这些文件，这些目录，
You know, the files, the files, the directories,
它们都必须以某种方式在磁盘上表示，
they all have to be represented in some way on the disk,
因为如果你关机后，再回来，
because like after if you shut down your computer, come back up,
所有的数据还得在那里，
you know all the data still has to be there
所以在这个数据结构上
and so there's basically on this data structures
以表示文件系统的数据结构
to represent the structure of the file system
或者文件系统的内容。
or the content of the file system.
在 xv6 中，
In xv6,
当然表示或数据结构非常简单，
of course you know that representation or the data structures used are quite simple,
只是出于教学上的原因，
you know just do for pedagogical reasons
而真实的文件系统有更复杂的数据结构，
and real file systems more complex data structures,
但是你可以把它想象成在这个数据结构上。
but you can just think about this as on this data structures.
所以我们会在今天的课程中看到很多这样的内容。
And so we'll see a lot of that in today's lecture.
最后，让它变得有趣的是性能。
And then finally, what makes it interesting is performance.
通常存储文件系统的设备，
The devices typically on which you know file systems are stored
存储设备通常很慢。
you know stored devices are typically slow.
比如，读或写一个块，
That meaning example to read or write a block,
在 SSD 固态硬盘上的速度是 1 毫秒，
you know on a solid-state disk, SSD disk, that's going the order a millisecond
而在 1 毫秒内，你可以做大量的工作。
and so in the millisecond, you can do a ton of work.
所以，尽量避免使用磁盘是很重要的，
And so it's important that you're trying to avoid going to disk,
我们会看到有多种方法，
we'll see that in multiple ways,
我们会看到，
so we see that,
比如，所有文件系统都有某种缓冲区缓存
for example all file system will have something of a buffer cache
或块缓存。
or a block cache.
而且你还可以看到更多形式或更多的并发性。
And you also see it basically additional forms or more concurrency.
比如，如果你执行路径名查找，
For example, if you do a path name lookup,
通常是关联的操作，
you know, then that typically is involved operation
按层级查找目录，
required descending the directory hierarchy,
你查找目录[]，
you looking up [] for a directory,
在目录中查找文件名，
find the file name in the directory,
然后检查下一个目录，等等，
then go through the next directory, etc etc,
你想要的情况是，
and you wanted to be the case
如果一个进程正在进行路径名查找，
that if one process is doing path name lookup,
另一进程可以并发或并行运行。
another process can run concurrently or in parallel
与第一个查找路径名的进程一起。
with the first process doing a path name lookup.
所以我们会看到并发出现，
And so we'll see that sort of concurrency you know shows up
这也是文件系统中的一个大的话题。
again is a big topic in the content of file systems.
有趣的另一个原因是
The other reason why it's interesting is,
它将成为两个实验的主题。
it's going to be the topic of two labs.
我们接下来的实验将完全集中在文件系统上，
So we're gonna have next upcoming lab is completely focused on file systems
之后的实验是虚拟内存和文件系统的组合，
and the lab after that is a combination of virtual memory and file systems
即使是今天或本周的实验，
and even the lab for today or this week
也有一个组件试图让缓冲区缓存更加并行。
has a component to trying to make the buffer cache more parallel.
所以这就是为什么它很有趣的原因，
So that's why it's interesting
你应该开始
and you know just you should get off the ground
了解文件系统必须提供什么，
to understand what the file system must provide,
让我们再来看看基本的文件系统调用，
just let's look again at the basic file system system calls,
去看 API 示例。
right, to the API example.
如果你查看这些文件系统调用的 API ，
If looking at you know API, these file system calls,
然后我们可以看到这里有几个有趣的属性，
then we can sort of there's a couple of interesting properties,
关于实现，它们一定是真的。
that must be true about the implementation.
所以文件系统调用，
And so the, you know the file system calls,
我们在这个学期的早些时候就见过它们，
we've seen them early on in, in the semester
我们看过大多数其他 Unix 系统调用如何实现它，
and you know we've looked at most other Unix system calls how to implement it,
比如 dork exec 和管道，所有的东西，
like fork and exec pipes, all that stuff,
基本上，这几节课的重点是
and basically this set of lectures is really focusing on
如何实现文件系统调用。
how to implement the file system calls.
首先，让我们从一个简单的情况开始。
So, first of all, let's startup simple case with a simple scenario.
假设我们创建了一个文件 x/y ，
We have you know say we create a file x/y,
或者文件 y 在目录 x 中。
or file y in the directory x.
是啊，它可能，糟糕。
Yeah, it probably have to oops.
是的，在文件 x 中，
Yeah, in the file x,
我们必须提供一些标志，
we have to provide some flags,
我们并不关心这些标志，
we don't really care about the flags,
所以我忽略它们，
so I'm just going to ignore them,
所以，这将创建一个文件，
so this will create a file
返回文件描述符给调用者，
returns a file descriptor you know to the caller
然后调用者，用户应用程序可以写，
and the caller, the user application can then actually for example write,
通过这个文件描述符，
you know through that file descriptor,
就像我们之前看到的，
as we've seen many times before,
这里有 write(fd, "abc", 3) 。
there's a write fd, maybe abc, you know 3 characters.
还有一件事，
And one things,
已经有很多东西可以从这两个调用中看出。
actually you know already a couple things that we can point out right, from this two calls.
首先是路径名，
So that first of all, the path names,
它在接口中出现，
that show up in the interface
我们必须实现的，
and we're going to have to implement,
名字人类可读的，
names are hum- human readable,
它们不是数字，
they're not numbers,
它们是由用户选择的。
you know they get selected by the user.
这里另一个有趣的事情是，
Another interesting thing here is that,
在 write 系统调用中，
in the write system call,
没有偏移量作为参数，
there's no offset as an argument,
所以偏移量是隐式的，
so the offset is implicit,
所以文件系统某个地方必须存储偏移量，
so the file system somewhere must store the offset,
如果你第二次调用 write ，
if you do a second call to write,
write 最终，
write will end up as
下一组字节将写入到位置 4 。
you know the next set of bytes will written in that location 4.
也许有一些我们没有看过的更有趣的调用，
You know, so maybe some more interesting calls that we haven't looked at much,
比如， xv6 和所有 Unix 文件系统
for example, you know the xv6 and all Unix file systems
基本上都支持创建链接的调用，
basically support calls to create links,
为了使同一文件具有多个名称，
to have multiple names for the same files for the same file,
比如，它可能调用 link ，
so for example it might call like link
为原始文件创建第二个名称，
that basically creates a second name for the original file,
比如，为我们之前创建的文件 y 创建名称 z 。
so for example, creates names z for the file y that we earlier created.
所以，多个名称，
So multiple names,
可能文件系统内部需要以某种方式跟踪，
the file system probably internally has to keep track you know in some way,
多个名称可能指向同一个文件。
that multiple names might be pointing to the same file.
我们可能会在文件打开时，删除或更改名称空间，
We might actually remove, or changed name space, while the file is open,
比如，我们可以调用，
so for example, we could call,
用户可能调用一个进程，
user might actually call that a process,
同一进程可能会调用 unlink 来删除指定文件。
the same process might call unlink you to remove a particular file.
事实上，我们删除了之前打开的文件 x/y ，
In fact you know we removed the file x/y that we actually open earlier,
但是我们仍然有一个打开的文件描述符，
but we still have a file descriptor open
所以我们仍然可以给它写入，
and so in fact you know we can still write to it,
所以我们仍然可以写入到 fd ，
so we can still write to fd,
比如字符，不管什么， d e 和 f ，
you know, for example the character whatever d e and f,
实际上，它一切都很顺利。
and it actually worked out fine.
所以当文件在使用时，
So basically while you know file file was used,
它周围的命名空间实际上是可以改变的。
the name space that surrounds it could actually be changed.
所以必须是这样的，
And so it has to be the case,
如果你看一下这个，
you know if you sort of look at this,
这些事情，
you know sort of things,
文件系统内部发生了一系列有趣的事情，
that there's a bunch of interesting things going on internally the file system,
比如，文件描述符必须关联，
for example the file system, file descriptor must be associated,
我们有一些与名字无关的对象，
we have some you know object that is independent of the name, right,
因为即使名字改了，
because you know even if the name changes,
文件描述符仍然指向或引用相同的文件对象。
the file descriptor still point or you know, references the same file object itself.
所以，如果你想一想，
And, so, in fact if you think about this,
情况肯定是这样的，
it has to be the case,
必须有一些文件的内部表示，
that basically there has to be some internal representation of the file
在操作系统中，
inside of the operating system,
与名称本身无关。
that's independent of the name itself.
所以我们马上就会看到，
And so we're looking at in a second,
但我还想在这里说明另一点是，
but there's one other point I wanted to make here is
文件系统的目标是
the goal of the file system is
实现像我们在这里看到的 API ，
to be implemented an API like the ones that we're looking here
它是一种典型的文件系统 API 。
which is a sort of typical file system API.
这当然不是能够访问存储系统的唯一方法，
You know, this is of course not the only way to be able to storage system
或者把信息存储在磁盘上，
or going to store the information on disk,
我们可以想象完全不同的 API 。
you know we could imagine completely different APIs.
比如，数据库，
And, for example, you know maybe the database right,
持久化存储一些数据，
store some data persistently,
但是对数据的访问提供了非常不同的编程 API 或用户 API ，
but access to the data provides very different programming or API user API,
跟文件系统相比。
than a file system does.
所以重要的是，要记住，
And so just important, to keep in mind that you know,
还有其他方法组织存储系统，
you know there's other ways of organizing storage systems
我们的重点将放在文件系统上，
and where our focus is going to be on file system,
通常由操作系统提供。
which is typically provided by an operating system.
而数据库通常在文件系统之上实施，
And databases are typically implemented on top of the file system
或者围绕文件系统的大部分工作中，
or most of work around the file system,
你不能直接访问磁盘。
you can't have direct access to the disk.
我们在聊天中有两个问题。
We have two questions in the chat.
好的。
Yeah.
让我，请继续问任何问题。
Let me, just going to ask any questions.
所以， link 递增对底层文件描述符的引用，
So link increments a reference to the underlying file descriptor
而 unlink 递减？
and unlink decrement?
是的，这是正确的，我们稍后再详细讨论这个问题。
Yes, that is correct, we'll talk a little bit more about it later.
这里的另一个问题是关于软链接和硬链接的问题。
Another question here is about a soft links versus hard links.
今天我不会讲的太多，
I'm not going to talk much about it today,
但是你将实现软链接
but you will be implementing soft links
在即将到来的文件系统实验中。
in the next in the file system lab that is upcoming.
xv6 本身实现了硬链接，
So xv6 by itself implements hard links,
你还要实现软链接。
and you implement soft links in addition.
还有问题吗，还有其他问题吗？
Any questions, other questions?
link 是在 inode 上操作，
The link operates on the inode
不是在文件描述符上，是吗？
not on the file descriptor right?
没错， link 在 inode 上工作，
That's correct, link work on the inode,
让我。
so let me.
让我们到那里。
Since let's go there.
所以，文件系统结构。
So file system structures.
那么文件系统维护什么样的结构
So what structure does the file system maintain
来实现刚才提到的 API 。
to implement you know this API just talked about.
所以首先最重要的属性是 inode ，
So first of all the most important property is the inode,
所以这是一个表示文件的对象，独立于名称，
and so this is the object that represents a file, independent of the name,
所以，文件信息，独立于名称。
so file info independent of name.
实际上， inode 的命名方式是
In fact, you know the way you know name actually inode this is
inode 数字只是一个数字。
inode number just literally an integer.
所以，文件系统内部引用 inode ，
So the file system internally refers to inode
是通过编号，而不是实际路径名称。
by number instead of actually by path names.
我们也知道，从这个讨论中知道，
And we also know this based on this discussion,
inode 必须有链接计数，
that you know inode must actually have link count,
为了记录，
to keep track of the number of,
为了记录名字的数目，
to keep track of the number of names,
它们指向特定的 inode ，
that are pointing to that particular inode
文件只能在以下情况下删除，
and the file should only be deleted
当链接计数为 0 时。
when the link count actually reaches zero no earlier.
这要稍微复杂一点，
It's actually slightly more complicated,
还必须有打开的 fd 计数，
there must be also an open fd count,
即文件具有的文件描述符数，
number file descriptors that actually have to file open
只有当这两个值都为零时，才能删除文件。
and file can only be deleted when both of these are zero.
我们也知道， write 没有偏移量，
And we also know that basically based on you know the write have no offset,
read 也没有，
nor does read,
所以，文件描述符必须隐式维护一个偏移量。
you know that the file descriptor implicitly must maintain an offset.
好的?
Okay?
所以，文件系统中的中心数据结构是 inode ，
And so basically the central really data structure in a file system is inode
然后是与进程交互的文件描述符。
and then a file descriptor to actually interact with the processes.
所以，即使文件系统在 API 方面非常相似，
So, even though the file systems are very similar terms short of their API,
它们的实现方式是不同的，
you know they're all implemented differently,
但它们中的许多都有一种类似的结构。
but many of them have a sort of similar structure.
而且因为文件系统相当复杂，
And because the file systems are quite complex,
将它们组织成一层，有助于组织它们。
you know just helps to sort of organize them in a typically organized in a set of layers.
我想的是，
And you know what I think about it,
在最下面，这是磁盘，
this is at the very bottom, there's the disk,
一些存储设备保存着这些数据。
some storage device that actually holds you know the data.
并且提供了持久性和耐久性，
And actually provides the persistence and durability
通常，这里有一些东西，
and typically you know there's something
比如缓冲区在它的上面，
like a buffer cache, a block cache right, above it,
为了避免访问磁盘太多。
so that to avoid going to disk many times.
所以我们把缓存数据放在内存中。
So we're gonna cache basically data inside in memory.
所以这是内存，
So this is going to be basically, you know memory,
这是设备。
and this is the device.
对于持久性，通常会提供记录层，
For persistence, there's something typically offer logging layer,
很多文件系统具有某种形式的日志记录。
you know many many file system have a form of logging.
我们周三会更多地讨论这个，
We're going to talk mostly about it Wednesday,
所以我先跳过这个话题。
so I can skip that.
在 xv6 中的最高层，
Then the top of the layer locate in xv6,
有一个 icache ，就是 inode 缓存，
there's an icache where inode cache,
这主要是为了同步，
this is mostly for synchronization,
我们也稍后再谈。
let's also talk about a little bit later.
所以 inode 通常比磁盘块要小，
So inode you know typically smaller than disk block
许多 inode 打包到一个磁盘块中，
and many inodes are packed into a single disk block
为这些单独的 inode 提供同步，
provides synchronization to those individual inode,
xv6 维护着 icache 。
you know xv6 maintains icache.
然后是 inode 本身的实现，
And then typically that you know were inode the implementation itself,
读取和写入字节。
you know that sort of ranges for read and writes bytes.
然后在它之上，
And then you know on top of that,
我们有名称，比如路径名和文件描述符操作。
we have names, like path names and file descriptor operations.
无论如何，每个文件系统的组织方式略有不同，
Anyway, every file system be slightly differently organized
并且层也可能略有不同，
and layers may be slightly different,
也许层并不总是那么严格，
maybe layers is not always that strict,
即使是 xv6 ，它也不总是非常严格的，
even xv6 it's not always super strict,
但是这是一个很好的思考方式，
but it is conceptually good way to think about it
几乎所有文件系统都有组件
and almost all file systems have components in their file systems
对应于不同部分，
correspond to the different pieces,
有缓冲区缓存、日志记录、 inode 和路径名。
you know the buffer cache, the logging, to the inodes and to path names.
所以工作是通过，
And so you know basically work by through a little bit,
通过这些不同的文件系统层。
through these different file system layers.
让我从最底层说起。
Let me talk a little bit of starting with the bottom layer.
只是看一下聊天。
Just looking at the chat.
所以，让我从存储设备开始说起。
So let me start with a talk a little bit about storage itself, storage devices.
有很多不同类型的存储设备，
It turns out there are many many, many different types of storage devices,
有不同的性能、容量和耐久度，
in the difference between performance you know capacity, degree of durability,
但是最常见的两个是，
but you know two of the common ones you know are
你们可能很熟悉 SSD 固态硬盘，
you know you're probably all familiar with you know the SSD,
也有有些人可能
and there maybe you know some people
只是简单地说选择硬盘或磁盘。
may simply mean choosing hard disks or magnetic disks.
你知道它们提供了大量的存储空间，
And you know they provide a ton of storage,
以合理的价格，以不同的性能，
in reasonable cost, in different performance,
SSD 通常具有
so SSD have typically in the order of
数百微秒到毫秒级的访问时间，
hundreds of microseconds to the milliseconds access time,
而磁盘通常是十毫秒级，
well magnetic disks tend to be more in the order of ten milliseconds
对于单个读写块来说。
to individually read or write a block.
这里的术语有点困惑，
The terminology is actually slightly confusion here,
术语扇区，还有块，
you know, the terms sector, that are used blocks,
历史上扇区是最小单位，
and so in sectors typically the historically the smallest unit,
磁盘可以读取或写入，
that disk drives can can read or write in
所以通常是 512 个字节，
and so you know should be typically five hundred twelve bytes just a common number,
而块大小通常，
the block size is basically
块通常是操作系统或文件系统的说法，
where a block is basically an OS or a file system idea
或者是由文件系统定义的，
or defined by a file system
比如在 xv6 中是 1024 字节，
and in xv6 for example it is 1024 bytes,
所以这是两个扇区，
and so it's two sectors,
通常情况下，块的大小是一个或多个扇区。
so typically the block sizes one or more sectors.
有时，人们也将磁盘上的扇区称为块，
Sometimes people refer to the sectors on disk also as blocks
所以术语不是特别精确。
and so you know the terminology is not particularly precise.
这些设备是连接在某个总线上，
So these devices you know basically sit you know on some bus,
总线连接到 CPU 上，
and you know the bus is connected to the CPU right,
内存可能在这边，
you know there might be memory on the side here,
可能有多个 CPU ，
maybe multiple CPUs,
文件系统运行在 CPU 上，
in the file system that runs on the CPU,
将其内部数据结构保存在内存中，
stores its internal data structures in memory
对 SSD 或硬盘的读写，
and basically reads and writes you know to to the SSD or the hard disk
是写入块或读取块。
to actually write a block or read a block.
所以，接口非常简单，
And so to actually interface is quite simple,
它通常只是使用块编号读或写。
so it's typically just read you know or write with block number.
这有点过于简单化了，
There's a little bit of oversimplification,
但是接口的核心大概就是这样的，
but like the core of the interface is roughly that,
在内部，固态硬盘和硬盘的工作方式完全不同，
internally, of course SSDs and hard disk to work completely differently,
但是硬件将大部分抽出，
but hardware extracts mostly away
通常是某种标准协议，比如 PCI 或 PCIe ，
and typically they're sort of standard protocols like PCI or PCI extended,
这是处理器或文件系统用户磁盘驱动程序
that's the processor or the file system user disk drivers
用于与磁盘交互，
used to actually talk to disks
通常从磁盘驱动来看，
and often from the disk driver,
大多数磁盘看起来都是一样的，
you know most disks you know sort of look the same
只需要提供一个块编号和一些数据就可以读写，
and you can just read and write by providing a block number and some data
把它发出去，
and then you know send it off
或者写入设备的控制寄存器，
or write to control registers you know the device
设备就会完成它的工作。
and the device will do its job.
从文件系统的角度来看，
And so this from file system perspective,
虽然磁盘有非常不同的，
although you know the the disk have quite
存储设备有非常不同的属性，
storage device have quite different properties,
从驱动的角度来看，
they're actually, from the driver's perspective,
你可以用大致相同的方式编程。
you know so you can program in roughly the same way.
有什么问题吗，
Any questions about that,
我不会太多谈论存储设备，
I'm not gonna talk much about the storage devices,
所以如果你有任何问题，
so if you have any questions,
现在是提问的好时机。
this is a good time to ask them.
是的，我有个问题，
Yes, I have a question,
用于调用读或写的接口是否
is the interface for calling read or write something
提供了同步和异步选项。
that offers synchronous and asynchronous options.
是的，通常都是这样的，
Yeah, often this is the case,
它非常类似于，
in fact it's generally like it's almost very similar to
你可以考虑磁盘的驱动程序
actually, basically you can think about the driver for a disk
与控制台驱动程序相同的方式，
in the same way as the console driver
CPU 或驱动向设备发出命令，
where the CPU or the driver issues a command to the device,
开始读或写，
basically say start to read or do write
然后在设备完成后的某个时刻，
and then at some point later when the device is done
然后生成一个中断，
and will generate an interrupt
表示，好的我已经完成了读或写，
saying like okay, I did the read or I did the write
然后这意味着完成了。
and then you know that indicates the completion.
当然，驱动程序，
And you know of course, the driver,
因为这个设备比控制台更复杂，
since this device is more complicated than the console,
它的驱动程序比控制台驱动程序要复杂得多，
you know it's quite a bit more complicated driver than the console driver
我们在上一节课中看到的，
that we saw in the previous lecture
基本上是相同的结构，
was basically the same structure,
下半部，上半部，中断，
bottom half top half, interrupts,
以及读取或写入控制寄存器。
and reading or writing to control registers.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thanks.
好的，从文件系统的角度来看，
Okay, so, so from the file system perspective,
考虑磁盘的方式非常简单。
the way to think about the disk is pretty straightforward.
有一个读写块或扇区，
Since there's a read or write of block or sectors,
但我们可以想象一下，
but we can just think about
磁盘是巨大的块数组，
the disk basically gigantic you know array of blocks,
从 0 开始，
you know starting at you know whatever zero,
然后是 1 ，
you know one,
然后增加到磁盘的大小。
and going up to whatever the size the disk is.
文件系统的作用是
And basically the file system's job is
在磁盘上放置所有数据结构，
to sort of layout all the data structures on the disk,
以一种可以在重启后重新构建文件系统的方式。
in a way that you can reconstruct the file system after reboot.
所以有不同的方式去做，
And so you know there are different ways of going about it,
xv6 使用非常简单的布局结构，
xv6 you'll see uses a very simple layout structure,
但是，不是完全使用，
but, but not completely use,
典型的文件系统操作。
you know pretty typical in or prototypical for how file systems operate.
所以，通常块 0 不使用，
So typically the block zero is generally not used
或用于引导扇区以引导操作系统。
or used actually for the boot sector, to boot the operating system.
块 1 通常是所谓的超级块，
Block one is often what's called a super block,
超级块描述了文件系统，
and the super block basically describes you know the file system,
它可能会说磁盘上有这么多块，
and it may say like oh there's so many blocks on disk
它们构成了文件系统，
and that constitute the file system,
稍后我们会看到，
and we'll see in a second,
xv6 在其中包含了更多信息，
xv6 is a little bit more information in it,
像大多数其他文件系统一样。
as in make most other of file system.
例如，在 xv6 中，
For example, in xv6,
日志从块 2 到块 32 。
the log starts at you know block 2 and runs into block 32.
是的，这是日志。
Yeah, so this is the log.
当然，日志可以有不同的大小，
And of course the log could be different size
事实上，在超级块中，
and in fact in the super block,
写着日志的长度是 30 个块。
it just says like the log is whatever 30 blocks long.
然后，在 xv6 中，从块 32 到 45 ，
Then, xv6 after that, stores from 32 to basically block 45,
如果我没记错的话，
if I remember correctly,
保存这 inodes ，
it's stores inodes,
就像我之前说的那样，
as I said before,
多个 inode 打包成一个单独的，
multiply inodes are packed into a single,
这个块我想 inode 是，
this block I think inode is,
我想，我不记得了，
I believe, I don't actually remember at the top of my head,
但我认为它是 64 字节，或 128 字节，我相信是 64 字节。
but I think it's either 64 bytes, or 128, I believe 64.
在那之后，有一个 bitmap 块，
And after that you know there's a bitmap block,
是我们构建文件系统的详细方式，
it turns out in the detail way we build the file system,
这个 bitmap 块是一个块的大小，
this next bitmap block one block in size,
这些跟踪数据块，
and so these basically keep track of actually the data blocks,
它是不是空闲的。
whether it's free or not.
在那之后，从这里到那里，都是数据块，
And after that, it's all for basically here to there, it's all data blocks,
数据块保存文件内容或目录内容。
so data blocks that actually stored contents files or contents of directories.
通常所有 bitmap 块和 inode 块以及记录块，
Often all the bitmap blocks and inode blocks and logging block,
有时称为元数据块，
often sometimes referred to as metadata blocks,
它们并不存储实际数据，
they don't actually store actual data,
但它们为文件系统保存元数据信息来完成工作，
but they help you know they store meta information for the file system to do its job,
比如位图和索引节点。
like bitmaps and inodes.
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Any questions so far about this?
我有一个关于引导块的问题，
I have a question about the boot block,
它是否包含用于引导操作系统的代码或其他内容。
does it contain the code for the operating system to boot or something else.
是的，没错，它通常包含一个块代码，
Yeah, exactly, it typically contains you know one block of code,
足够让操作系统开始运行，
enough for the operating system to get going
然后，可能会从文件系统加载操作系统的更多部分。
and then load maybe more of the operating system actually from the file system itself.
谢谢。
Thank you.
那么这是否意味着 xv6 的代码实际上存储在虚拟磁盘上，
So does that mean that the code for xv6 is actually stored on the virtual disk,
或者是怎么回事。
or is it like how does.
xv6 我们使用 QEMU ，得到一些[]，
Xv6, you know the way we do with QEMU, you know we got some [],
QEMU 有一个标志， -kernel ，
QEMU actually has a flag, you know -kernel
它指向引导内核的位置，
that basically points to the where boots the kernel from
然后加载到一个特定的地址，
and loads you know that at a particular address
到物理内存中， 0x80000 ，
into physical memory at 0x80000,
所以当我们使用 QEMU 时，
and so basically when we're using QEMU,
按照我们使用 QEMU 的方式，
the way we use QEMU,
我们不必担心引导扇区或类似的事情。
we don't really have to worry about boot sectors or anything like that.
好的，所以当你运行 QEMU 时，
Okay, so basically like when you run Q- QEMU,
你只要就像通过命令行一样把程序传进来，
you just you just pass in like the the program through the command line,
然后它就会运行它，
and then it'll just run that,
它不需要从虚拟磁盘和其他东西中读取它。
it doesn't need to read it from the virtual disk and everything.
理解了。
That makes sense.
好的，就像，比如，
Okay, so like in the, so for example,
所以假设我知道 64 个字节，
so assuming I know such 64 bytes,
现在如果你想读取 inode 10 ，
you know for example, now if you want to read inode 10,
你应该怎么做。
what do you do.
如何读取 inode 10 ？
How do you read inode 10?
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
inode 10 在哪个块上？
Which block do inode 10 be?
你需要加上，
You'd need to add,
使用 inode 编号加上偏移量，
you take the inode number and add the offset into the [],
所以是 10 加 32 。
so 10 plus 32.
所以是 32 加 10 或者其他的东西。
So 32, right, and it literally plus 10 or something else.
是 10 除以大小吗？
Is it 10 divided by the size.
是的， inode 编号，
Yeah, it's gonna be whatever it's gonna be inode number,
inode 编号乘以，我们以字节为单位，乘以 64 ，
inode number multiplied times, we do it in bytes, multiply it by 64,
除以 1024 ，
divided by 1024,
所以， inode 0 最终出现在块 32 中，
so inode 0 will end up in block 32,
无论哪个 inode ，
inode whatever,
1024 除以 64 是多少？
what was 1024 divided by 64?
16？是的， 16 ，
16? Yeah 16 that's all right,
所以 inode 17 会在哪里，
so inode 17 where will where will it end up,
应该在块 33 ，对吧。
should be in, should be in block 33 right.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
所以，给出 inode 编号，
So given inode number,
我们就可以在磁盘上找到 inode 存储的字节。
we can always find the bytes on disk where inode actually stored.
好的?
Okay?
好的，我们来看一下，
Okay, so then let's look at the,
在磁盘 inode 上的实际是什么。
what actually is in on disk inode.
根据我们知道的，
So as we know it before,
你将看到数据结构， 64 字节大小，
you'll see there's basically little data structure, 64 bytes in size,
通常有一个 type ，
and you know typically has a type,
我们稍后会谈到，
which we'll talk about it later,
比如 type 是文件或目录。
but for example type file or directory.
还有 link ，
And link,
link 计数跟踪多个名称或指向同一 inode 。
you know the link count to track multiple names or pointing to the same inode.
还有以字节为单位的 size 。
Size in bytes.
在 xv6 中，文件系统中的这些略有不同，
And then in xv6 you know there can be slightly different in the file system
具体的表现形式是，
and exactly how the representation is,
在 xv6 中，
but in xv6,
多一点空间。
a little bit more space.
在 xv6 中，后面跟着的是块编号，
In xv6 basically is followed by a number of block numbers,
所以，后面是块 0 ，块 1 ，
and so after, block number 0, block number 1,
实际上，有 12 个这样的块编号，
in fact, there were twelve of those guys,
这 12 个直接块编号，
these 12 direct block numbers,
这些直接块编号
and those direct you know block numbers
对应于构成该文件的前 12 个块。
basically correspond to the first 12 blocks that constitute that file.
如果文件只有两个字节长，
So, for example if the file was only two bytes long,
这里只有一个块编号 0 ，
you know there would be only one block number 0
块编号 0 是磁盘的块编号，
and block number 0 is that the block number of the disk block
它包含该文件的前几个字节。
that contains you know the first few bytes of that file.
然后有一个间接的块编号，
And then there's one indirect block number,
这是一个块编号对应于一个块，
basically that's a block number, that corresponds to a block,
它本身的块是 1024 字节，
which then itself block is 1024 bytes,
保存 256 个块编号。
which holds 256 block numbers.
所以从块编号 0 到 11 都是直接块编号，
So from block number 0 to block number 11 are all direct block numbers
然后是块编号 12 保存那个间接块，
and so then block number 12 you know stored in that, in that indirect block,
指向间接块编号。
basically pointed to by the indirect block number.
这就是 xv6 中文件的布局。
And that is basically the layout of the file in xv6.
那么基于这个， xv6 中的最大文件是多少呢？
And so what is the maximum file size in xv6 based on this.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
它是 268 乘以 1024 字节。
It would be 268 times 1024 bytes, basically.
是的， 256 加上 12 个直接块编号乘以 1024 ，
Yeah, where just 256 plus 12 direct times 1024
我们就得到了以字节为单位的最大文件大小。
and then we get the maximum file size in bytes, right.
它是多少？
How much is that?
换个说法，它是 268 千字节。
Another way of saying it's basically two 268 kilobytes, correct.
你能在 268 千字节中存储什么？
What can you store in 268 kilobytes?
你能在里面存储视频或者一首歌吗？
Can you store video in it or a song?
如果是一首短歌，是的。
If it's a short song, yes.
很短的歌，是的。
Very short song, correct.
所以这些文件非常小，
So these are really small file size,
真实的文件系统文件要大得多。
real file systems has much much bigger file size.
那么，如何处理文件系统表示，
So what would you do to file system representation
可以让文件变得更大。
to make this, to allow the files to be much more files to be much bigger.
你可以增加间接的部分吗？
Could you extend the indirect portions.
是的，比如，你可以在下面有另一个块，
Yeah, like for example you could have another block seating here below, correct,
可能是两倍间接，
which is maybe double indirect,
就像我们以前看到的那种页表类型的数据结构一样，
almost like you know the sort of the page table type data structures that we've seen before, right,
那个双倍间接块指向 256 个间接块编号，
that double indirect block points to 256 indirect block numbers,
每一个都指向另一个块编号，
each which point to another block number,
最大文件尺寸要大得多。
and so certainly the file size is going to maximum file size is much there.
只是对这些数据结构的一种练习，
And basically just turned out to be just a sort of exercise in on those data structures,
你可以选择类似的数据结构，比如树，
you could pick a structure like this, like tree,
但也有可能实现为 B-Tree 或其他复杂的东西。
but there's also possible to like maybe implemented as B-Tree or something other sophisticated,
xv6 是非常简单的，
xv6 something extremely simple,
基本上它是仿照最初的第六版 Unix 。
basically it's modeled after the original version six Unix Unix.
但你可以让使用更复杂的方案，
But you can make them more sophisticated schemes,
事实上，在文件系统实验里，
in fact in the file system lab,
你可以实现双倍间接块编号来支持更大的文件。
you will implement double indirect block numbers to support much bigger files.
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
抱歉，是 256 个块吗，
Sorry, so is it 256 blocks,
因为就像一个整体的块，
because it's like one block as a whole,
间接块。
indirect.
这是一个间接的块编号，所以这不算，
What this is an indirect block number, so that doesn't count,
所以间接块中有 256 个，
so there's 256 sitting in this indirect block
加上 12 个直接的块编号，就是 268 个。
plus 12 direct block numbers that makes it 268.
哦，抱歉，我的问题是为什么是 256 。
Oh, sorry, my question was why is it 256.
哦，因为可能块编号是 4 个字节。
Oh, because it's a block number 4 byte probably.
所以 1024 除以 4 是 256 个条目。
So 1024 divided by 4 is 256 entries.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thank you.
这也是有点[可笑的]，
Which is also a little bit ridiculous,
如果块编号只有 4 个字节，这个能有多大？
if block number is only 4 bytes, how big can this be.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
2 的 32次方，对吧，
Two to the power 32 right,
有些东西比这更大，
some things are bigger than that,
所以，通常人们使用比 32 位更大的尺寸来存储块编号。
and so typically you know people use larger sizes for block numbers than 32 bits.
好的?
Okay?
有什么问题吗，更多的问题？
Any questions, further questions?
对于最大文件大小，
For the max file size,
您能再解释一遍吗，比如。
could you could you help explain that again, like.
好的，当然可以。
Okay, sure.
每个块能不能，
Could each block in the,
间接块引用的每个块，
could each block in, that's referenced by the indirect block
能不能指向更多块，
could that also point to more blocks,
如果有用的话。
if that makes sense.
在默认的 xv6 设计中，不是这样，
In in the default xv6 design, that's not the case,
基本上 12 个直接块编号，
basically the 12 block numbers, 12 direct block numbers
和 256 个间接块编号，
and 256 indirect block numbers
没有其他了。
and nothing more.
在下一个实验中，
In in the next lab,
你要给 inode 添加一个双重间接块，
you'll be adding a double indirect block to the inode,
所以你要从 bn0 到 11 中选择一个，
so you'll take one of these bn0 11
把它变成一个双重间接块。
and turn that into a double indirect.
而这个双重间接块将指向，
And that double indirect going to point to,
这里我们有有 256 个的间接块编号，
this we have 256 indirect block numbers,
然后，它本身指向块。
which itself then point to you know blocks.
现在，文件可以放在那里。
Now, the way file can be substantially there.
哦，好的，谢谢。
Oh okay, thanks.
好的，现在，让我们看看实现 read 系统调用。
Okay, so now, let's say we want to implement the read system call.
我们从操作系统引导开始，
And, you know basically we start from operating system boots
要读取字节 8000 。
wants to read say byte, read byte 8000.
是的，你怎么知道读哪个块，
Yeah, how would, you know, which block would you read,
哪个块包含字节 8000 。
which block will contain basically byte 8000.
你如何计算或如何查找，
How would you compute or how you would look up,
给出这个数据结构，
giving this data structure,
这个非常简单的数据结构，
this extremely simple data structure,
你怎么计算出块编号，
how would you compute the actually the block number
或者找出包含字节 8000 的块编号。
or find the block number that contains byte 8000.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
你是不是减去，
Do you just subtract,
比如，首先减去前十二个直接块的字节数。
like, first of all subtract the number of bytes in the first 12 direct blocks.
嗯。
Hmm.
然后看看间接块中的偏移量是多少。
And then see what the offset is in the indirect blocks.
是的，所以好的，在 8000 的情况下，
Yeah, so okay, so in case of 8000,
我们做的是除以 1024 ，
what we will do correctly divided by 1024,
因为那是块大小，
because that's the block size,
结果是 7 ，对吧。
and that is 7, right.
这意味着第 7 个块，
And so that means that basically the 7th block
在直接块编号里的第 7 个，
actually has the 7th entry in this direct block number,
有包含字节 8000 的块编号。
has the block number that contains you know byte 8000 correct.
所以 bn7 不管块编号的什么数字，
So bn7 whatever number is there is the block number,
包含这个特定的文件，
that contains this particular file file,
字节 8000 找出那个字节在块中的确切位置，
byte 8000 to actually find out exactly where that byte is inside of that block,
我们用 8000 对 1024 取模，
you know basically we have to compute 8000 delivery by 1024,
我想大概是 832 。
which is probably I think it's 832.
好的，所以要读取字节 8000 ，
Okay, so basically to read byte 8000,
文件系统会查看 inode ，
you know the file system looks at the inode,
取字节数除以 1024 ，
takes the byte number divide 1024,
进入索引，
indexes into,
查看是否小于 12 ，然后是一个直接块编号，
see see if it falls below 12, then as a direct block number
只需从 inode 获取直接的块编号，，
and just picks up the direct block number from the inode
读取块，然后取出 8000 字节，
read that block and then fishes out you know 8000 byte
通过计算 8000 对 1024 取模，
by computing 8000 divided by by module 1024 and
它会给我们偏移量 832 ，
so it will give us an offset of 832
这就是文件的 8000 字节的位置。
and that's the location for byte 8000 that file.
好的?
Okay?
所以，这些信息足够得出结论，
So basically, this is enough information to conclude from,
现在这里有足够的信息
this is like there's enough information here now
来实现 read write 系统调用，
to actually implement read, write system calls,
至少找出哪些磁盘块需要读取或写入，
at least to find out which disk blocks need to be read or written,
对于读或写系统调用。
in response to read or write system call.
好的。
Okay.
让我简单地谈一下目录。
So let me talk a little bit about directories.
关于文件系统最酷的事情之一，
One of the cool things about you know file systems,
有一个分层的名称空间，
where you know have a hierarchical name space
你可以使用用户友好的名称，
and you can store store symbolic user friendly names
在文件系统中。
inside of inside of the, inside of the file system.
有趣的是，
And the interesting aspect actually,
一个很酷的设计是，
one of the cool design features is,
大多数 Unix 文件系统所做的，
most Unix file systems actually does,
目录基本上就是文件，
directory is basically the file,
除了文件具有某种结构,
except the file with some structure,
文件系统理解的。
that the file system understands.
事实上，在 xv6 中，数据结构非常简单，
In fact, in xv6 you know the structure is extremely simple,
目录由目录项组成。
every, the directory consists of directory entries.
而每个条目都有固定的格式，
And every entry has a fixed format,
它在前两个字节中包含 inode 编号，
namely it contains an inode number in the first two bytes,
在剩余的 14 个字节中包含文件名，
and it contains a filename in the remaining 14 bytes
所以总共是 16 个字节。
and so the total thing is sixteen bytes.
这些信息基本上已经足够了，
And, this is enough information basically for,
我们实现了路径名查找。
you know we actually implement path name lookup.
所以，比如，更清楚一点，
So, for example just to make it clear,
假设我们想要查找路径名 y/x ，
let's say we want to look up the path name y/x,
我们该怎么做呢？
how we go about doing that?
你知道这个路径名表示，
So well, you know this path name explain, indicates
我们必须从根 inode 开始。
that we have to start at the root inode.
通过它，
And it turns out that through that,
有一个固定的 inode 编号，
then basically has a fixed a fixed inode number,
根 inode 编号有一个预先定义的固定编号，
the root inode number has a pre agreed fixed number
在 xv6 中，这个数字是 1 。
and in fact in xv6 that number is 1.
那么我们如何找到根 inode 编号呢？
So how can we find the root inode number?
现在我们回到之前的图片，
Now we go back to our earlier picture, right,
是的，它是编号 1 ，
yeah it's number 1,
我们知道 inode 从块 32 开始，
you know we know that you know inode start at block 32,
所以它一定是块 32 ，
so it must be thirty block 32
所以在第 1 个块的字节 64 到 128 ，
and so it's the byte 16 to whatever byte 64 to 128 in that first block,
包含根 inode 编号，
that contains the root inode number
所以，文件系统可以读取根 inode 编号。
and so the file system can just read the root inode number.
好的?
Okay?
然后按照路径名查找和工作的方式，
And then basically the way path name lookups and works,
它查看块，
it just scans the blocks,
你知道名字 y ，
therefore, you know the name y,
所以文件系统通过，
so the file system basically go through
到达 inode 所在的块，文件 inode 1 ，
reach the blocks of the inode, file inode one,
一个接一个，
one by one
查看这些块的数据，
and just looks you know for the data of those blocks
看字符串 y 是否存在。
whether the string y appeers.
它如何找到 inode 1 的所有块，
And how can it find all the blocks of the inode 1,
看 bn0 ，第一个块，
well, just look at the, reach the bn0 the first block,
查看 x 是否在其中，
you know sees if x in that,
如果不是，会读取第二个块，等等，
you know if it's not, will read the second block, etc etc,
直到在某一时刻，
until hopefully at some point,
它要么找到它，要么找不到它。
either it finds it, or doesn't find it.
如果它找到它，
And if it finds it,
让我们找文件 x ，
let's find file x,
在目录中，会有 inode 编号，比如 251 ，
in the directory was going to have so inode number say 251,
然后我们就可以从那里开始了，
and then we can just proceed from there, right,
我们可以说，好的，
we can say it's like, well okay, well,
现在读取 inode 251 ，
now read you know block number, you know read inode 251,
查看它的块。
and scan its blocks for.
好的，我做错了我的例子，
Okay, I just did my example wrong,
这是 y ，它会获取 x 的块。
this is y, and it's going to block for x.
然后，我们，
And [] was going to find us,
所以 inode 编号，
you know, so inode number again,
我们会把它作为路径名查找的结果返回。
we'll return that as a result of the path name lookup.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
你知道。
Would you say you.
这个。
So, this.
是的，这是磁盘中目录的布局，
Yeah, so this is the layout of the directory in the disk,
但是，在元数据块中的是否有一些位，
but is there some bits somewhere in the metadata blocks
指示当前是目录还是文件。
that indicates whether the current thing is a directory or a file.
是的，它实际上在 inode 中，
Yeah it's actually in inode,
inode 的类型说明了是目录或文件，
so the type of the inode says what's a directory or file,
如果你查找，
so if you do look up on
而 inode 是一个文件，
and inode that actually happens to be a file,
那么文件系统会返回一个错误。
then actually the file system will return an error.
我明白了，谢谢。
I see, thanks.
好的?
Okay?
很明显这种数据结构并不是特别高效，
Now, clearly this structure is not particular efficient,
要找到目录名，你必须扫描，
you know to actually find a directory name, you have to scan,
一个真正的文件系统可能会使用更复杂的数据结构，
and so a real file system you know probably would use more sophisticated data structures,
让这种查找比 xv6 快得多。
to actually make this lookups much faster than xv6 does.
但是，这是一个关于数据结构设计的问题，
But, again it's sort of almost you know a more design question of data structures
而不是操作系统设计的问题。
than is a question of operating system design.
你可以使用你最喜欢的数据结构，
And so you could plug in your favorite data structure
并将它转换[]数据结构，
and turn it into an [] data structure,
然后希望能获得更好的性能。
and then hopefully you're going to get better performance.
但是为了简单和容易解释，
But for simplicity and ease explanation,
这里是非常简单的数据结构。
you know actually is very simple structure.
好的?
Okay?
好的，接下来我要做的是
Okay, so what I wanna do next is
对这个有更具体的感受，
going to get a little bit more concrete feel for this
看看在 xv6 中实际是如何工作的，
and just to see actually how things work out in practice in xv6
这对下一个实验是很有帮助的。
and this will be helpful you know for the next lab.
我要看一下 xv6 ，
I'm going to look at xv6 for a second,
通常的 screen 。
usual [screen].
所以，我要重启 xv6 的第一件事，
So, the first thing I'm gonna boot xv6 again,
它总是，我输入 make clean ，
it's always and I did make clean,
你们可能还记得，
and as you probably remember
或者你们中的许多人都遇到过这种情况，
or many of you have run into this,
你需要新的文件系统，
you know you want actually new file system,
你必须运行 make clean ，
you have to run make clean,
因为，然后 make qumu 将会构建一个新的干净的文件系统。
because then make qemu will build you a new clean file system.
所以我们开始吧。
So here we go.
我们看到 xv6 已经启动，
And we'll see that xv6 has started,
但是我首先要指出的是，
but the thing I want to point out first is,
在这里，你看到有一个调用创建一个文件系统，
here, here, you'll see there's a call to basically make a file system,
所以这会产生一个新的磁盘镜像，
so this makes a fresh disk image,
在磁盘映像中包含了一些文件，
in the disk image contains you know a bunch of files,
我们在命令行中指定的，
that we specify on the command line
并使它更快，
and make it fast,
创建包含那些文件的 QEMU 文件系统，
basically built QEMU file system that contains those files
那些文件作为文件系统内容。
as the contents of the file system.
你可以看到 xv6 ，
And you can see you know the xv6
提供了一些关于文件系统的信息，
which brings out a bit of information about the file system,
它表示有 46 个元数据块，
so it basically says there are 46 meta blocks,
包括启动块，超级块，
you know that includes the boot block, the super block,
30 个 日志块， 13 个 inode 块， 1 个位图块，
the 30 log blocks, 13 inode blocks, one bitmap block
然后是 954 个数据块，
and then followed by 954 data blocks,
所以这是一个很小的文件系统，
so it's a tiny file system
总共只有 1000 块。
in total of only thousand blocks.
你们在实验中要做的一件事是，
And one of the things you will do in the, the lab,
支持更大的文件，
to support bigger files,
你还必须使用更大的文件系统。
you also will have to use a much bigger file system.
然后，我稍微修改了 xv6 ，
Then I modified xv6 slightly
来写或打印一些东西。
to basically write or print something
当我们写入特定的块的时候。
whenever we write to a particular block.
比如，我们看到几个文件系统调用，
So for example, we see a couple file system call,
在 xv6 启动时，
xv6 when it starts up
执行了一系列文件系统调用，
does a bunch of file system calls
写了块 33 33 46 和 32 。
and apparently wrote block 33 33 46 and 32.
我们要执行指令，
And we're gonna run basically command
我们要查看，
and we're just gonna see
哪些块编号被写入，
what block numbers are being written
是由那个命令引起的，
by that command or cause of that command
我们要理解，
and we've been trying to understand
这些 write 是什么意思，
where do where do those writes make sense,
我们想看到它们是否真的，
what we expect to see if they were actually,
看看发生了什么才是我们真正期待的。
to see what is happening is what we actually expect.
所以我要创建一个文件，
So I'm going to create a file,
echo hi,
是的，我要创建一个文件 x 。
yeah, I'm gonna create a file x.
让我把它复制出来，
And let me actually copy that a little bit over,
这样我就可以标记这个，
so I can delineate this,
我将在几个地方标记，
I'm going to delineate in a couple places
为了帮助理解，
just for help for understanding,
可能在这里，
probably right here,
然后可能在这里。
then probably here.
好的。
Okay.
基本上这里有几个阶段，
It's basically it turns out there's gonna be a couple phases here,
一个是创建文件的阶段，
one is the phase to actually create the file,
然后是写文件，也就是 write hi ，
then, there's write the file, namely write hi to file
然后再写一次，
and then one more write,
写入换行到文件中。
write actually the new line into the file.
所以，你可以查看 echo 程序，
So you look at the echo program,
这就是它所做的。
that is basically what it does.
我可以把它找出来，
I can actually pick it up,
为了[完整性]，
just do it for completeness, right,
所以， echo ，看看它的参数，
so echo, look at his arguments,
write 的参数写入文件描述符 1 ，
write's arguments to file descriptor 1
然后在末尾添加一个换行。
and then at the end of the appends a new line.
好的?
Okay?
所以，这些就是每个操作中涉及的磁盘写入序列。
So, these are basically the sequences of disk writes get involved in each operation.
让我们依次看看，
And let's go look at them one by one
试着理解发生了什么事。
and start to understand what's going on.
我要做的，
I'm going to basically,
可能是最简单的事情，
maybe the easiest thing to do
把这个移过去。
actually used to, move this over.
好的，所以很方便理解发生了什么，
Okay so, it's convenient to understand what's going on,
我们不看代码，
instead of looking at the code,
而是只看这个磁盘布局，
we're going to just look at this disk layout
试图弄清楚，
and trying to figure out
在这些特殊的操作中可能会发生什么。
what might be going on in these particular operations.
好的。
Okay, good.
那么我们怎么看这个 write 。
So what do we think this write is.
有人知道这是什么吗？
Any idea what this might actually be?
我们在创建一个文件，
We're creating a file,
那么我们期望文件系统做什么。
so what do we expect file system to do.
它写入了 inode 条目。
It writes the inodes entry.
是的，所以第一件事是，
Yeah, so first thing I was just to,
好的，它是 33 ，
so okay so it's 33,
我们对块 33 有什么了解？
so what do we know about block 33?
如果我们看一下磁盘布局图。
If we look at the disk layout picture.
它包含一个空闲 inode 。
It contains a free inode.
是的，它包含，
Yeah, you know it contains,
我们知道 inode 1 在 32 ，
we know that inode one lives in 32, correct,
所以我们分配的 inode ，
and so we're whatever apparently inode that's being allocated is
可能是位于块 33 的 inode 。
probably at inode that lives in block 33.
假设第一次写入可能只是标记，
Presumably the first write might just be marking
这个 inode 是要使用的，
you know that this inode actually is now going to be used
所以我认为 xv6 的实现方式是，
and so I think the way xv6 does is
它在 inode 中使用 type 字段，
it uses the type field in the inode
指示 inode 空闲，文件或目录，
to actually indicate where inode free, file or directory,
所以它从空闲变成文件，
so it basically changes from free to file
并写入磁盘，标记为已使用。
and write to the disk to mark it as in use.
我们认为下一个 write 33 是什么？
What do we think next write 33 is?
填充 inode 条目需要信息。
Actually, populating the inode entry would like info.
是的，确实填充 inode 信息，
Yeah, exactly yeah, indeed populating an inode info,
inode 可能有条目，
you know inode probably with entries
比如将链接计数设置为 1 ，或类似的东西。
like setting the link count one and things like that, right.
46 是什么，
What is 46,
我们期望 46 32 是什么，
what do we expect 46 to be in 32,
它可能是什么。
maybe that's there.
46 是第一个数据吗，
Is 46 the first data,
不，是位图。
no, actually bitmap bitmap.
不，它只是一个数据块，
No, it's just a data block
你说得对，这是第一个数据块。
and you're right it's the first data block.
那么你认为这是谁的数据块？
So whose data block do you think is this?
是根目录条目？
It's root directory entry?
是的，没错，这可能是块，
Yeah correct, this is this is probably the block,
根目录的第一个块，
first block of the root directory,
是 inode 1 ，对吧。
you know inode one, right.
我们为什么要写入它，
And why were we expecting to actually that to be written,
发生了什么。
what has.
因为我们正在创建 x ，
Because, because we're, we're creating like x in,
我们将一个新文件 x 添加到当前目录中，
we're adding a new file x to the current directory,
将它添加到文件层次结构中。
so adding it to the file hierarchy.
是的，没错，我们这样做，
Yeah, exactly, so we have we've done this
我们刚刚在根目录中添加了一个条目，
and we just added an entry to the root directory,
即条目 x ，使用我们分配的 inode ，
namely entry x with whatever inode we allocated,
在一两步之前。
you know the step, two steps before.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
那么我们认为 write 32 是什么？
So what do we think is write 32 is?
对于块 32 ，
To block 32,
那么现在要做的是，
well, the thing to do is
回去看看磁盘布局图。
go back and look at the disk layout picture.
块 32 是什么？
And what is block 32?
可能是 inode 1 。
Inode 1 probably.
是的，它将包括 inode 1 ，
Yeah, well, it will include inode 1,
包括所有其他 inode ，
includes all the other inodes correct,
因为 inode 比块小，
because inode is smaller than a block,
但它将包括 inode 1 。
but it will include inode 1.
你认为它为什么写入，
Why do you think it's going to be written
inode 中可能发生了哪些更改，
what what might have changed in the inode
需要 inode 实际写入磁盘。
that requires that the inode actually written to disk.
大小。
Size.
是的，大小改变了，
Yeah, the size change exactly,
大小改变了，
size change,
因为我们将目录增加了 16 个字节，
because we grew the directory correct by 16 bytes
保存条目 x 。
to actually store entry x.
然后还有一个写入 33 ，
Then there's one more write to 33
我暂且不提这个，
and I'll leave that hanging for a second,
基本上，我们再次更新 x 的 inode ，
basically we're updating inode for x one more time,
即使没有写入什么。
even through nothing actually what's written yet.
好的?
Okay?
所以这是第一阶段。
So that's the first phase.
现在我们来看第二个，
So let's now look at the second,
所以有创建，
you know so there's creation,
现在我们来看一下第二阶段，
now let's look at the second phase
或者第一次写入，
or the first write
将 hi 写入到文件 x 。
you know write hi to file x.
好的，我们认为 45 是什么？
Well, what do we think 45?
位图？
Bitmap?
是的，是位图，
Yeah, it's the bitmap,
这里发生的事情是，
so presumably what happened to here is does that
文件系统扫描位图块，
file system scan the bitmap block
为了找出没有使用过的块，
to find a block that was not used,
找到位 0 ，然后设置为 1 ，
so find bit 0 and then set that bit, you know to 1
表明这个块现在正在使用。
to indicate that that particular block now is in use.
所以它写入 45 到磁盘中，
And so it wrote you know 45 to to disk,
更新位图块。
updated the bigmap block.
你觉得位图分配器选了哪个块？
What block do you think the bitmap allocator picked?
595？
595?
是的，很有可能，
Yeah, most likely, correct,
因为紧接着我们看到写入 595 ，
because right after it we see you know write to 595,
很可能这个块是分配给文件 x 的。
and presumably the block that was allocated to the file x.
所以，在 inode 中，
And so basically in the inode correct,
文件 x 的 bn0 是数字 595 。
file x now in bn0 will have the number 595.
那么第一个字节是什么，
And, and basically what will be the first byte,
在这个写之后，块 595 的第一个字节的值是多少。
what's the value of the first byte of block 595, after this write.
H.
H ，是的。
H, yeah.
第二个写的是什么，这一个。
What do we think the second write is, this one.
i 。
i.
是的，是 i ，
Yes, i right,
因为每个 echo ，字符是一个接一个的，
because every echo, you know there's a character by character.
好的，我们认为这个 33 是什么？
Okay, what do we think this write 33 is?
再次更新大小。
Updating the size again.
是的，更新 inode 的大小，
Yeah, updating the size of the inode,
因为现在它有两个字节。
that's because now it has two bytes in it.
这能理解吗？
Does it make sense?
问题， 595 看起来在磁盘中的位置很高，
Question, 595 seems very high up in the disk,
那是因为那里目前有着其他的东西，
that because there's other stuff that's currently living there
比如内核引导代码和其他已经启动的东西吗？
like the kernel boot code and other things that have already been start?
是的，我们可以回到这个屏幕，
Well, yeah we can go back to the this screen,
我们可以看看 make fs 做了什么，
we can look at what make fs did, right,
所以 make fs 在那里存储了很多文件，
so make fs stored a whole bunch of files there,
在我们创建文件 x 之前。
in the files that before we actually created file x.
我们创建了所有这些文件。
And in fact we've created all these guys.
所以很大一部分磁盘已经被文件填满了，
And so it was only a good chunk of the disk is already filled by the files,
相当数量的块已经被这些文件使用。
the for blocks, a good number of blocks already used basically by the set of files.
明白了。
Got it.
写入块 595
Would it write down that block 595
是否与上次的 inode 有关，
is related to that to that inode during the last,
比如在 write 32 。
like during the write 32 that.
是的，完全正确，
Yeah, exactly correct,
这个写入 33 可能有很多东西发生，
so there's write to 33 probably a bunch of things happened correct,
大小更新了，
the size got updated,
并且 bn0 和 bn1 更新了，
and you know bn0 and bn1 were updated,
抱歉，只有 bn0 被更新，包含 595 ，
sorry, only bn0 is updated, correct, to contain 595
这些信息都被更新到 inode ，
and both pieces of information are updated inode
然后写入磁盘。
then written to the disk by this write.
能理解吗?
That makes sense?
是的，谢谢。
Yeah yeah, thank you.
很好，这就是磁盘布局的本质，
Good, so that's you know sort of the essence of disk layout
希望你能很好地理解
and hopefully you have a pretty good understanding
这些是如何工作的。
of what goes on to make this work.
所以现在我们将更详细地看一下，
And so it's going to look a little bit more in detail,
在代码中，
now at the code,
看看更多一个层次的细节。
to see actually things little, one more level of detail.
好的，重新分 inode 后的第一件事，
Okay, so the first thing since reallocated inode,
我们先来看看是怎么发生的，
let's first look at actually how, how that happened,
所以，在 sysfile 中，让我们看一下[]。
so in sysfile, let's see [].
这里是与文件系统调用相关的所有调用，
So here're all the calls related to file system calls,
发生的第一件事是 sys_open ，
so the first thing that actually happens, correct, it was sys_open,
因为我们要创建一个文件，
because we're going to create a file,
因为 open 要调用 create ，
since open will call create,
这里是 create 。
here's create.
create 稍后将看到，
Create we'll look at this later,
将路径名解析为最后一个目录，
resolves the path name to basically the last directory,
遍历目录，然后查找，
walks the directory and then does look up
并真正关心的，
and really care about that
看看文件是否已经存在，
just to see if the file already exists,
如果文件存在，可能会返回错误。
and if the file exists, you know maybe you're return an error.
然后它调用 ialloc ，
And then it calls inode allocate
这是那个调用，
and so this is the call
为文件 x 分配 inode ，
that is going to allocate this inode for the file x,
让我们看看，它在 fs.c 中。
so let's look that, it's gonna be fs.c.
这里是 alloc ，
And here is ialloc,
像大多数 xv6 代码一样，
like most xv6 code,
它非常简单，
you know it's just very simple,
但性能不是特别高。
but not particularly efficient.
它所做的是，
And so what it does,
它遍历所有的 inode 编号，
basically it goes for all the inode numbers possible,
从 1 到任意最大 inode 数，
from 1 to whatever the maximum number of inode
在这个特定的文件系统上，
that as a possible on this particular file system,
然后到达那个 inode 编号的块，
and then reach block for that inode number,
所以，从 1 开始，
so, for example starts with one,
包含 inode 编号 1 的块，
which you know the block contains an inode number one
然后查看那个 inode 编号是否可用，
and and then sees if that inode number is free
如果它不是，
and if it's not,
如果它是空闲的，
if it is free,
然后把它设置给文件，
then it sets it to file,
通过这种方式将其标记为已分配，
and that way marks it as allocated
并写入磁盘，
and writes it to disk,
这个 log_write ，有我使用的 print 语句，
and this log_write, you know actually print statements I had,
我把它们放到 log_write ，
I put that actually log_write,
所以 log_write 是我们看到第一次写入，
so that log_write was the first write that we've seen,
以我们执行的写入顺序，
in that sequence of writes that we did,
文件系统说做的。
what file system do.
这能理解吗？
Does this make sense?
非常有趣，
So interesting,
所以这是一系列事件
so it's basically sort of the sequence of events
让你第一次写入磁盘，
that get you to the first write to the disk,
有趣的问题是，
interesting question of course,
如果多个进程同时调用 create 会发生什么，
what happens if multiple processes are calling create at the same time,
多核机器可以并行运行，
multi-core machine that can be running in parallel,
同时下来，几乎同时到达 ialloc ，
you know coming down and all get to ialloc roughly at the same time,
然后它们要调用 bread ，
and then all they're gonna call they're gonna call bread,
所以这里有一些故事，
so there has some story
或者这些写是如何彼此不干扰的。
or how is these writes don't interfere with each other.
是的，这很值得一看，
Yeah, it's really worthwhile looking into,
因为在某种意义上，这实际上是
because in some sense, you know this is actually
你正在做的实验的最后一部分，
the part of the last part of this lab that you're currently doing,
所以它会进入缓冲区高速缓存。
so it gets into the buffer cache.
那么让我们来看看 bread ，
So let's look at bread,
在 bread 中，第一件事是，
so on bread more the first thing
它调用 bget ，
it does actually it's called bget
bget 基本上是在缓冲区高速缓存获取一个插槽。
and so basically bget a slot in the buffer cache.
让我们看一下 bget ，
Let's look at the bget for a little while,
因为有一个非常棘手的代码。
because there's a reasonable tricky code.
那么，这里的前几行是怎么回事。
And, so what's going on in the first couple lines here.
我想你们中的一些人，已经详细看过了这段代码，
I imagine some of you already looked at this code quite a bit of detail
作为本实验的一部分，
as part of this lab,
锁实验。
the locking lab.
那么这里是怎么回事。
So what's going on here.
它对链表加锁，并检查是否有任何，
It locks the linked list and check if any of the,
查看缓存中有没有我们要找的东西。
things in the cache are maching with what we're looking for.
是的，所以这是缓存，
Yeah, so basically this is the cache,
实际上，我们要找的是
in action we're looking for
无论什么块编号，块编号 33 ，
whatever the block number, block number 33
我们查看缓存里是否已经有编号 33 的块。
and we're basically seeing if the cache already has block number 33.
如果是这样的话，它就会增加引用数量，
And and if that is the case, it bumps the ref count up
然后释放 bcache 锁，
and and then release the bcache lock,
因为我们已经完成了对缓存的查看，
because we're done looking into cache itself,
我们知道它在那里，
we know it's there,
我们知道那里有一个块的缓冲区，
we know that there's a buff- buffer for that particular block, there,
然后，发生的下一步是非常有趣的。
and, and then the next step that actually happens is sort of interesting.
下一步，块缓存会尝试获取缓冲区的锁。
Next step, the block cache basically tries to get a lock on the buffer.
所以，如果多个进程同时调用 bget ，
So, so what happens if like multiple processes at the same time called bget,
其中一个会获得 bcache 锁，对吧。
well one of them is going to get the bcache lock, right.
它会扫描缓冲区缓存，
It's going to scan the buffer cache,
没有人可以在特定时间内修改缓冲区缓存，
and so nobody can actually modify the buffer cache in this particular point,
找出块编号是否在那里，
find if the block number is there
如果块编号在那里，
and if the block number is there,
它会增加引用数量，
it bumps the ref count,
表明它有一个引用，
indicating that basically it has a reference,
对于这个特定的锁，
you know to this, this particular lock
然后释放 bcache 锁。
and then releases the bcache lock.
如果有第二个进程等待，
So if there were a second process waiting,
为了扫描这个缓存，
all to also scan the this cache,
它可能不能马上获得锁，
it might not actually require to lock right away, right,
可能是第二个扫描的进程，
in fact it might be a second process of scanning for,
也想扫描这个块 33 。
one also want to scan for this block 33.
它也会获得引用，增加引用计数，
And it will also get you know basically a reference to be bump the reference count,
到 2 或 3 ，不管是什么
to 2 or 3 whatever it is
然后它们两个都会试着调用 acquiresleep ，
and then you know both of them will try to call acquiresleep,
在那个特定缓冲器 33 上。
on that particular buffer buffer 33.
acquiresleep 是另一种类型的锁，
And acquiresleep it's just basically another type of lock,
我们称它们为睡眠锁，
we call them sleep locks
稍后我们会讨论，
and we'll talk about in a second,
基本上，这会获得缓冲区上的锁，
but basically you know this acquires the lock on the buffer,
所以，进程中的一个将获得缓冲器 33 的锁。
so one of the two processes will get the, the lock of buffer 33,
并将继续进行，并且返回，
and will proceed and that will be returned
并通过[]，
and go from going through [],
扫描块 33 ，
you know like scanning that block 33
看看是否 inode 是真正空闲的。
to see if there is inode that actually is free.
另一个进程在 acquiresleep 等待，
And the other process will just be sitting in the acquiresleep here,
等待第一个进程完成所有操作。
you know waiting until the first process is done with all its operations.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
我有个问题，
I have a question,
当块的引用计数不是 0 时，
while the ref count of a block is not 0,
关于块改变有没有什么重要的，
can anything important about that block change,
因为某些事情可能会发生，
because something can happen
在释放 bcache 和获取块的锁之间。
between the release of the bcache and acquiring the lock of the block.
是的，原则是，
Yeah, actually the the protocol,
好的，这里我要说明几个点，
okay, so there's a couple points I want to make here,
xv6 遵循的规则是
the protocol basically xv6 follows is
任何对于 bache 本身的修改，
that for any modification to the bcache itself,
你都需要持有 bcache 锁。
you need to hold the bcache lock.
对于任何对于块 33 的修改，
For any modification to this block 33,
你需要持有块 33 的睡眠锁。
you need to hold the sleep lock on block 33.
所以在任何特定的时间点，
And so at any particular point in time,
在释放之后， b->refcnt 大于 0 ，
so after the release, b->refcnt is a larger than 0
并且不会对缓冲器高速缓存进行修改，
and there will be no modification to the buffer cache,
缓冲器高速缓存只会驱逐，
buffer cache will only evict
或者具有引用计数 0 的东西，
or things that actually have the refcnt 0,
refcnt 不会有大于 0 。
never that has a refcnt of something bigger than 0.
所以我们可以肯定的是，
And so we know for sure
这个块，这个缓冲区不会接触 bcache 本身，
that this block basically this buffer won't be touched in the bcache itself,
其他进程可能正在查找，
you know other processes might be looking up,
可能正在查找 bcache 中的条目，
might be looking up the entry in the bcache,
但它不会从 bcache 中删除，对吧。
but it won't be removed from the bcache, right.
是的，理解了。
Yeah make sense.
而第二个锁，睡眠锁，
And this lock that second lock at this sleeplock
用来保护缓冲区的内容，
is really what protects the content of the buffer,
确保只有一个进程在读取或写入缓冲区，
ensuring that only one process actually will be reading or writing the buffer
在任何时间点。
at any particular point of time.
这很重要，
And it's important, correct,
会有什么不好的，
that can it say, would be bad if like say what would be bad
如果块 33 在缓存的不同的插槽中出现两次。
if block 33 ended up in the cache twice in different slots.
是的，因为那样任何都会有正确的信息了，对吧。
Yeah, because then any could have the correct information, right.
是的，没错，
Yeah correctly,
比如，进程 1 写入 inode 19 ，
for example let's say process one writes inode 19
而另一个进程写入 inode 20 ，
and the other process writes inode 20, correct,
所以，如果它们都获得了缓冲区的句柄，
and so if they both get a handle on the buffer,
表示块 33 ，
for that represents you know the the block 33,
一个可能更新 inode 18 ，
one might update inode 18,
另一个是 19 ，
the other in 19,
第一个可能安排 18 写回到磁盘上，
the first one maybe arrange its 18 back to the disk,
然后修改 19 的进程写回到 19 ，
then the guy that does modified 19 write 19 back,
会覆盖 18 所做的更改，
will overwrite changes at 18 made, right,
是 inode 18 所做的。
that were made for inode 18.
所以这太可怕了，
And so that's terrible,
所以，必须是这种情况，
so it has to be the case
块编号只能在缓冲区缓存中出现一次。
that the block number only appears in the buffer cache only exactly once.
这里有一个不变量，
And there's an invariant, correct,
你需要维护，
you know you sort of have to maintain
当你做块缓存实验，锁实验时，
while you're doing this a block cache lab, locking lab
本周的实验里。
in this week's lab.
这能理解吗，那个不变量？
Does that make sense, that invariant?
是的，这是个离题的问题，
Yeah, I guess tangential question to this,
可能有一些块有多个引用，
there might be some blocks that have multiple references to them
然后可能其中一个进程接触到这个块，
and then maybe one of the processes that has is touching this block
通过强制写入磁盘来刷新高速缓存，
flushes the cache by forcing a write to the disk,
其他人看到的东西会发生什么。
what happens to what everyone else sees.
是的，就像我做的，如果写，
Well, as I did, if the write,
好的，第一个进程在某个点上完成了，
okay, so the first process is done at some point,
会调用 release ，
will call release [] whatever it's called,
所以你可以想一想，
so basically you can think about
当第一个进程完成，
at the end when the first process done
通过读写块 33 ，
with it's reading and writing to that block 33,
它会调用 brelse 释放那个缓存，
it will call brelse release with a buffer,
这会减少 refcnt ，
and that will actually decrease the refcnt,
releasesleep 锁，
well, releasesleep lock,
也就是说，如果有人在等，
and that means that if anybody was waiting,
任何其他等待特定缓冲区的进程，
any other processes was waiting for that particular buffer
现在能够获得缓冲区上的睡眠锁，
and will now be able to get the sleeplock on the buffer
会看到之前做的修改。
and go read, it will observe the preview than you make changes, right.
所以，如果两个进程返回，
So if two processes were returning
更新 inode 18 和 inode 19 ，
to the update inode 18 and inode 19,
它们都在块 33 上，
that all both live in block 33,
那么如果第一个过程完成了，
then if the first process is done,
它修改的 18 是可见的，
it changes 18 are visible
所以下一个，
and so the next
下一个进程会分配 inode 19 ，
and so the next guy will actually allocate inode 19,
因为现在 18 已经标记为文件了，
because actually 18 is marked as a file now,
后面的任何进程都会观察到这些变化。
anybody afterwards will observe the changes.
理解了吗?
Makes sense?
好的，谢谢。
Yes, thanks.
这正是我们所希望的情况，
And this is exactly what we hoped would be the case,
如果一个进程创建 inode 或创建文件，
if one process creates an inode or creates a file,
那么后面的进程读取，
then the process, later process does read,
应该能观察那个文件。
you know should observe that file.
好的，因为一个更小的细节，
Okay, then, because one more smaller detail,
正如你在代码中看到的，
as you can see here in the code,
在进程中对缓冲区使用了睡眠锁，
in the process actually takes a sleeplock on the buffer
所以睡眠锁与普通锁或旋转锁略有不同，
and so the sleeplock is slightly different than a regular or a spin lock,
让我们来看一下睡眠锁。
let's look at sleeplock for a second.
你会看到它是什么。
And you see what it is.
所以我们需要获取睡眠锁。
So we need to acquire sleeplock.
是的，当它发生的时候，
Yeah, and when it does,
它获取某些字段，
it requires you know some field,
获取与睡眠锁相关的自旋锁，
basically requires a spin lock that is associated with sleeplock,
如果锁真的被持有了，
if the lock is actually held,
好的，旋转锁被持有了，
okay, the spin lock is held,
那么，如果锁真的被持有了。
then, if the lock is actually held.
好的，让我先看看头文件，
So okay, let me first see h file,
头文件包含一个 locked 字段，
the h file contains a locked field,
然后，就这样了。
and, and that's it.
所以，基本上。
And so basically.
那是自旋锁。
That was the spin lock.
是的，是自旋锁。
Yeah, we're spin lock.
哦，是的，这是自旋锁。
Oh, yeah, there's a spin lock.
很好。
Good good.
抱歉，如果锁持有了，
Sorry, and then if the lock is actually held,
睡眠锁被持有，它进入睡眠状态。
sleeplock is held it actually goes to sleep,
它会自行排定调度。
so it deschedules itself.
为什么对这些缓冲器
And why, why do you think for these buffers are
我们使用睡眠锁而不是自旋锁，
we using sleeplocks instead of spin locks,
因为我们间接地使用自旋锁来实现休眠锁，
because indirectly we're using spin locks to implement sleeplocks,
为什么不直接用普通的呢？
why not just use regular?
因为磁盘操作需要很长时间？
Because disk operations take a long time?
是的，原因有很多，
Yeah, there's multiple reasons,
在自旋锁上有各种各样的限制，
there's all kinds of rules correct restrictions on a on a spin locks,
自旋锁的限制之一是什么。
what is one of the restrictions on spin locks.
你要做什么。
Well, what do.
中断必须关闭。
Interrupts have to be off.
是的，它们会关闭中断。
Yeah, they turn interrupts off, right.
所以我们开始这个操作，
And so we were we started this operation,
在缓冲器上持有自旋锁，
while holding a buffer, while holding a spin lock on the buffer
然后我们再也不会从磁盘让出。
and then we would never yield from the disk.
嗯，也许还有另一个核心，
Well, maybe another core here,
但是如果我们只有一个核心，
but if we had only one core
我们永远不会从它让出，是吧。
and we would never yield from it, right.
出于同样的原因，
And for more, for the same reasons,
你不能持有自旋锁进入睡眠。
you know you're not allowed to go to sleep, while holding a spin lock.
所以，我们有了这些睡眠锁，
And so therefore we have these sleeplocks,
这是一种长期的锁，
that are sort of long-term locks,
对于这个特定情况。
if you will, for for that particular use case.
所以我们可以持有锁，
So that we can hold locks,
睡眠锁的优点之一，
one of the advantages of sleeplocks
我们可以持有它们通过中断，
that we can hold them across interrupts,
因为磁盘操作，
hold, because disk operations,
我们可以长时间持有它们。
we can hold them for long periods of time.
如果我们在等待那把锁，
And we're not, if we're waiting on that lock,
我们也不会让 CPU 保持忙碌，
we also not keeping the CPU busy
或花费在 CPU 上，
or spending on the CPU,
我们通过调用 sleep 来释放 CPU 。
we're basically releasing the CPU by calling sleep.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
好的，我们再来看一件事，
Okay, let's look at one more thing,
这就是 brelse 。
which is brelse.
所以我们已经看了一点，
So we looked already a little bit,
brelse 释放睡眠锁，
you know basically would brelse does releases the sleeplock,
然后获取 bcache 锁，减少 refcnt ，
then acquires the bcache lock, decrement refcnt
表示一个进程对这个缓冲区不再感兴趣。
to indicate that one process is not interested anymore, in this particular buffer.
然后，如果 refcnt 为 0 ，
And then, if if the refcnt is 0,
它稍微操作一下缓冲区列表，
the, it manipulates the list of buffers a little bit,
它在这里做什么。
what does it do here.
它将 b 插入到列表中 b->head 之后。
It inserts the b into the position after b head, inside of the []list.
是的，这是它做做什么，
Yeah, where does it basically go,
那是什么意思。
what does that mean.
让我们返回，让我们来看看。
So let's go back up, correct, let's look at.
它是最近使用过。
It was most recently used.
是的，移动到最近使用的缓冲区的位置。
Yeah, basically moves into the position of the most recently used buffer, right.
这一点很重要，
And this is important,
因为当我们在块缓存中找不到块的时候，
because when, when we cannot find the block in the block cache,
那么我们需要一些东西来腾出空间，对吧。
then we need to fix something to make space, right.
所以我们遍历块，
And so we're going to go through the block as we go
我们从最近使用的一个开始。
and we basically start from most recently used one.
先想一想这一点。
And think that one first.
所以，我们使用缓冲区，可能刚刚逐出。
And so we just used the buffer as very unlikely, that it actually evicted.
为什么这是个好的策略。
Why is that a good policy.
通常情况下，系统服从时间局部性。
Generally, systems obey a temporal locality.
是的，如果块是最近用过的，
Yeah right, so if the block is recently used,
这可能是一个很好的迹象，
it's probably a good indicator,
表明它可能会很快再次被使用。
that it might actually be used again quickly.
所以不把它赶出去是个好主意。
And so it's a good idea not to evict it.
你想要，通常情况下，
You wanna and it's generally sort of
即使有本地缓存，
if you even you have locality cache locality
最近最少使用的块，
and the block that is you know least recently used
可能是未来最有可能使用的块，
probably the block that is also most likely to be used in the future
所以，这是一个很好的[驱逐]。
and so that's a good one to evict.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的。
Okay.
所以，让我回到幻灯片上，
So, let me go back to my slides here,
所以， bcache 代码中有一点小偏差，
so, so there's a little bit of a slight excursion
在块缓存中。
in the bcache code or the block cache.
在这里有几个有趣的事情，
There's a couple interesting things at the point at to, correct,
有一个不变量，
you know there's this invariant,
内存中只有一份块的副本。
that there's only one copy of a block in memory.
作为重要的变量
And as an important variant
必须由块缓存维护，
that must be maintained by block cache,
它有睡眠锁，
it has sleeplocks,
和我们以前见过的不同类型的锁，
you know different types of locks than the ones that we've seen before,
它可以跨越 IO 操作，实现 LRU ，
that can span IO operations that implements you know LRU,
最近最少缓存替换策略，
least recently caching replacement policy,
需要有两个级别的锁，
need to have these two levels of locking,
在它的实现中，
to, in its implementation,
一级是为了保护 bcache 内部数据结构，
one level to basically protect the bcache internal data structures,
然后另一级锁，通过睡眠锁对不同的缓存加锁。
and then one level of locking through sleeplocks to actually lock individual buffers.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的。
Okay.
我的时间快用完了，
I'm going to run out of time,
所以让我停在这里，
so let me stop here,
很快总结一下我们到目前为止所看到的，
you know quickly summarized what we've seen so far
在下周三，
and we're going Wednesday
我们将关注崩溃安全问题。
and we're going to focus really on crash safety.
文件系统在这个数据结构上，
So basically you know file system is on this data structure,
今天演讲的大部分时间，
basically, most of the lecture today,
我们都集中在数据结构上，
we're focusing on the layout of the on this data structure
对于 xv6 ，磁盘上的这个数据结构，
of the xv6 you know this data structure on disk
我们看到 xv6 有一个非常简单的。
and you know we saw xv6 has a very simple one.
但是你可以想象一下，
But you can imagine
比如实现更复杂的。
like you know implementing more complicated one.
我们花了很多时间的另一件事是
And the other thing that we spend much time
查看这个块缓存，
looking at is this block cache,
这对性能至关重要，
which is crucial for performance,
因为对磁盘的读写是昂贵的，
because reading and writing typically to disk is actually expensive,
那里有几百微秒到几毫秒的时间，
you know we're there for hundreds of microseconds to milliseconds
块缓存可以确保，
and the block cache basically ensures that,
如果最近从磁盘读取了块，
you know if a block was recently read from the disk,
我们不会再从磁盘中读取它。
we're actually not reading it again from the disk.
好的，然后是周三，
Okay, and then Wednesday,
我要谈的是崩溃安全，
I'm going to talk about crash safety,
是文件系统设计的另一个吸引人的方面，
which is a fascinating other aspect of file system design,
事实上，我们将花两节课来讲解崩溃安全问题。
in fact we'll spend two lectures on crash safety.
我们将在周三看到一个慢的日志设计，
We'll see a logging design on Wednesday that's slow
然后在下周，
and then next week,
我们将了解 Linux ext3 如何进行日志记录，
we'll look at how Linux ext3 does logging
是一个更快的方案。
which is a much more faster scheme.
如果你有任何其他问题，
If you have any other questions
请随意提问，
feel free to hang around
我很乐意回答，
and I'm happy to answer them,
否则，周三见。
otherwise, you know, see you Wednesday.
好的，谢谢。
Alright, thank you.
我有一个关于 brelse 的问题。
I have a question about brelse.
是的。
Yes.
看起来像是它释放了块的锁，
So it seems like it releases the block's lock
在它修改了 refcnt 之后。
and after that it modifies the refcnt.
嗯。
Um.
为什么这样可以？
Why is that okay?
是的，好问题。
Yeah, good question.
所以我们知道，
So what do we know,
假设我们释放了睡眠锁，
you know, so let's say we do release the sleeplock,
如果其他程序正在等待，
so if some other guy or some other process actually was waiting,
或者要获取睡眠锁，
or what doing acquire sleeplock,
这对 refcnt 是什么意思？
what does that mean about the refcnt?
它是 0 ？
That it was 0?
不，
No, correct,
如果 n 个进程正在等待缓冲区。
so if n processes are waiting for a buffer.
哦，好的。
Oh okay.
refcnt 是什么？
What's the refcnt?
至少是 1 。
There was at least 1.
是的，多于 1 ，
Yeah, more than one, correct,
如果 10 个进程正在等待，
if 10 process you're waiting,
则 refcnt 会是 10 。
the refcnt can be 10.
是的，好的。
Yeah, okay.
所以，这一行代码，
And so, is this only this only line of code
它所做的，
what it does is
就是更新一个 refcnt ，
basically it updates the refcnt for just one guy
就是执行释放的进程，
which is one process that actually did the release
并且它将 refcnt 减少 1 。
and it reduces the refcnt by 1.
如果其他人在等待，
And if other people were waiting
refcnt 肯定不是 0 ，
and never refcnt was definitely not 0,
它永远不会执行这个代码。
will do, it will never execute this code.
好的?
Okay?
好的，好的，我明白了，
Okay, Okay, I see,
我想我明白了。
I I think I see okay.
一个更进一步的问题是，
A rather question was
为什么两个字节对于 inode 编号是足够的。
why is why is two bits, two byte enough for inode number.
它不是，它小得离谱，对吧，
It's not, it's ridiculously small, correct,
因为你可以拥有多少个 inode ？
because how many inodes can you have?
2 的 8 次方？
Two to the power of eight?
是的，随便吧，两个字节。
Yeah, yeah yeah yeah, whatever two byte.
16 位。
Sixteen bit.
[] [] ，32000 个 inode 。
[] [], thirty two thousand inodes.
对于 20 世纪 60 年代或 70 年代来说，这是很多的 inode ，
That's a lot inode for 1960s or the 60s and 70s,
但对今天来说肯定是不够的。
but certainly would not be sufficient for today.
所以，今天的文件系统使用更大的数字或更多的位。
And so, today's file systems use a bigger number or more bits.
好的，我明白了。
Okay, I see.
我想我的问题是
I guess my question was
关于 xv6 的架构，
in the architecture that we have for xv6,
这 16 位的 inode ，
the those two 16 bit for inodes,
它们在哪里，
like where where else do they,
我们还能在哪里看到这个数字出现。
where else can we see this number show up.
好的，它是两个字节，
Well, the the one that is two bytes
在磁盘上，它是两个字节。
is really on disk that it is two bytes.
任何数字，
Any number in
当它编译时，
when it's compiled,
当它位于寄存器或内存中时。
when it's sitting in a register or sit in memory.
磁盘 inode 是，
The disk inode is,
让我看看，
look at it, let's see,
正如之前所说的，磁盘 inode 实际上是，
so this disk inode as we said before actually the,
使用一个直接条目，
use a direct entry
我们看到是一个无符号短整型，
where we see is unsigned short
而[另一个]则是两个字节的 16 位。
and others there's two byte sixteen bits.
inode 在内存中表示形式，
The in-memory representation of an inode,
好的，是在，
you know, okay, that's in,
在内存中表示的 inode ，
you're doing in-memory representation of an inode,
这个数字是整型，
that actually number is integer
你知道我们编译 C 代码的方式，
and you know the way we compile C code
而整型恰好是 4 个字节。
and integer happens to be 4 bytes.
好的，我明白了，谢谢，非常感谢。
Okay, okay I see, thank you, thank you so much.